all right
[Music]
African Americans have a higher burden
of cardiovascular disease and diabetes
and other American ethnic groups but
recent evidence indicates that eating a
plant-based diet may help eliminate such
Health disparities as I explored
previously
African Americans as a group tend to
have the highest reported meat
consumption and the lowest vegetable
consumption and part of this is access
but this article detailing the
experience of a Morehouse Lifestyle
Medical Clinic noted that there also
appears to be an issue with aspects of
the African-American food culture
enter the regards study the reasons for
Geographic and racial differences in
stroke study the study found that
regardless of where African-Americans
live in the United States they are much
more likely to consume what the
researchers called a southern diet which
is a dietary pattern characterized by
added fats fried foods eggs organ Meats
processed meats and sugar sweetened
beverages they found that this type of
dietary pattern mediates the majority of
the racial disparity
adherence to the southern dietary
pattern increased stroke Risk by 39 in
Black Americans in contrast the greatest
benefit was seen among participants who
followed a more plant-based dietary
pattern which converted 29 lower stroke
risk same thing with heart failure
eating more plant-based was associated
with a 41 lower risk of heart failure
while the southern dietary pattern was
associated with a 72 percent higher risk
and this is after controlling for things
like education and income
death from kidney disease same thing
more plant-based linked to lower risk of
mortality whereas even closer to the
southern diet associated with a greater
risk of kidney disease mortality those
eating more southern style diets
likewise had a 56 higher Hazard of acute
heart disease
this finding was particularly
interesting dietary patterns in the risk
of sepsis sepsis is the syndrome of
bodywide inflammation triggered by
infection and is a major public health
problem that's how an infection can kill
you now we know diet plays a vital role
in immune Health but its association
with sepsis was unclear but a southern
dietary pattern of eating was associated
with higher risk of sepsis as well
particularly among black participants
what about cognitive function once again
greater consumption of the Southern
dietary pattern was associated with
worse outcomes lower scores and the
assessments of each of the cognitive
domains like learning and memory whereas
greater consumption of the plant-based
pattern was associated with higher
scores here's the data on learning the
more plant-based people ate the better
they were at a learning task meanwhile
The More Southern style people ate the
worse they were at learning same thing
with memory better the more plant-based
worse The More Southern style is
therefore possible that the increased
prevalence of Alzheimer's and African
Americans could be partially reduced via
dietary modification
easy for privileged me to tell people to
eat healthier but isn't it expensive to
eat plant-based uh have you seen the
price of beans there's this common
misconception that plant-based diets are
more costly than animal-based ones so
proper education will be needed a
vegetarian diet could result in
approximately 750 dollars per year in
savings so healthier and cheaper what
would you do with an extra 750 in your
pocket not to mention all the health
care cost savings
I mean a plant-based dinner consisting
of red beans brown rice collard greens
sweet potato and Cornbread could feed a
family of four for under 12 or three
bucks per person and check it out some
of the healthiest foods on the planet
are some of the cheapest foods such a
meal would not only be cost effective
but nutritious providing a mountain of
nutrition plus a host of antioxidants to
protect against various diseases like
heart disease and cancer
here's the save 750 bucks a year eating
more plant-based study why because
you're cutting out meat poultry seafood
and when one considers total grocery
costs animal products can be the most
expensive components costing more than
double the cost of a serving of
vegetables or legumes like beans but
peas chickpeas and lentils
foreign